Halperin, Rick; Papers apap108
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Court Files, 1988-1999; 3; 0.33 cubic ft.
  - Bruce Edwin Callins Case, United State Court of Appeals, 1994 February (Box 1 (3-Court Files), Folder 6c.)
  - Dorsie Lee Johnson Bey Case, Supreme Court of the United State, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Court Files), Folder 6d.)
  - Texas Special Issue System, Vernon's Texas Statutes and Codes Annotated Code of Criminal Procedure, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Court Files), Folder 6e.)
  - Amendment to Florida Rules of Criminal Procedure Rule 3.112 Minimum Standards for Attorneys in Capital Cases, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Court Files), Folder 6f.)
- Organization Files, 1984-2000; 4; 0.77 cubic ft.
  Series 4 is composed of organization files. The following organizations, advocating the abolition of the death penalty, are included: Amnesty International (AI), Amnesty International USA (AI USA), American Civil Liberties Union, Death Penalty Information Center, and NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Inc. The files are arranged alphabetically by the name of organization with materials within the files arranged chronologically.
  The Amnesty International files includes C2, the campaigning magazine of Amnesty Informational, published on December 1996, and EINSPRUCH, the magazine of Amnesty Informational, Hamburg, in German, released in 1994 and 1995.
  The Amnesty International USA files contains organizational reports, magazines, mailings from 1993 to 1995, newsletters, publications, campaign materials, and Halperin's notes for the briefing of the Amnesty International USA in 1987 and 1989.
  The American Civil Liberties Union file includes an organizational brochure, reports, and newsletter. This organization is devoted to defend and preserve individual rights by litigating, legislating, and educating the public on a broad array of issues affecting individual freedom.
  The Death Penalty Information Center is a non-profit organization serving the media and the public with analysis and information on issues concerning capital punishment. Included are research papers reported by this organization.
  The NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Inc. was founded in 1940 for the purpose of working for racial equality and social justice through legislation. The files of this organization consist of bimonthly reports, Death Row U.S.A., from 1984 to1994, and a report, Judicial Record of Justice William Rehnquist. These reports contains various statistical data of death row inmates, information on the death penalty statutes of each state, and a list of death-sentenced prisoners with information on their gender, race, and execution method.
  - Amnesty International, 4.1 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 1)
    - a.C2, 1996 December
    - b. Amnesty International Hamburg EINSPRUCH, May, July, September/October, November/December, 1994; 1995 August-1995 September
  - Amnesty International USA, Death Penalty Mailing, 1993 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 2)
  - Amnesty International USA, Death Penalty Mailing, 1994 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 3)
  - Amnesty International USA, Death Penalty Mailing, 1995 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 4)
  - Amnesty International USA, Halperin Notes, 1987; 1989 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 5)
  - Amnesty International USA, Human Rights Now, Campaign Papers, 1988 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 6)
  - Amnesty International USA, Human Rights Now, Press Clippings, 1988 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 7)
  - Amnesty International USA, Miscellaneous, 4.8 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 8)
    - a. Letter Writing Guide Sheet, Undated
    - b. Amnesty International USA Advertising Posters, Undated
    - c. Atlanta Olympics Death Penalty Action Papers, 1995 September-1996 July
  - Amnesty International USA, News, 1995-1997 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 9)
  - Amnesty International USA, Newsletters, 4.10 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 10)
    - a.Legal Support Newsletter, Spring 1994
    - b.Death Penalty Newsletter, 1995-1997
    - c.Abolition Network News, January/February, 2000
  - Amnesty International USA, Publications, 4.11 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 11)
    - a.Trainer's Handbook, 1991
    - b.Abolition Organizing Packet, 1998
    - c.Faith in Action, Abolition Resource for Congregations, 1998
  - Amnesty International USA, Reports, 4.12 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 12)
    - a. "The Death Penalty In International Perspective", 1991 December
    - b. "Moving Towards a World Without Executions: Obstacles and Hopes", 1992 January
    - c. "Open Letter to the President on the Death Penalty", 1994 January
    - d. "Failing the Future", 2000 April
    - e. "World Apart: Violations of the Rights of Foreign Nationals on Death Row Cases of Europeans", 2000 July
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 4.13 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 13)
    - a. Race and the Death Penalty, Fall 1987
    - b. Capital Punishment Project: A Report on Its Functions and Activities, 1992 January-1993 March
    - c.ACLU Abolitionist, Newsletter, v. 3, no. 2, 1996 April
    - d. ACLU International Civil Liberties Report, 1998 May
  - Death Penalty Information Center, 4.14 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 14)
    - a. "Millions Misspent: What Politicians Don't Say About the High Costs of the Death Penalty", 1992 October
    - b. "Sentencing for Life: Americans Embrace Alternatives to the Death Penalty", 1993 April
    - c. "Killing for Votes: The Dangers of Politicizing the Death Penalty Process", 1996 October
    - d. "Innocence and the Death Penalty: The Increasing Danger of Executing the Innocent", 1997 July
    - e. The Death Penalty in 2000: Year End Report, 2000 December
    - f. "Chattahoochee Judicial District: The Buckle of the Death Belt", Undated
  - NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Report, Death Row US, 1984-1987 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 15)
  - NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Report, Death Row US, 1988-1991 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 16)
  - NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Report, Death Row US, 1992-1994 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 17)
  - NAACP Legal and Educational Defense Fund, Report, Judicial Record of Justice William Rehnquist, 1992-1994 (Box 1 (4-Organization Files), Folder 18)
- Subject Files, 1982-1996; 5; 0.17 cubic ft.
  This series consists of subject files on the cost of capital punishment and mental retardation topics. Each file contains news clippings, articles, research papers, and other materials related to each subject.
  - Cost of Capital Punishment, 1982-1990 (Box 1 (5-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Mental Retardation and the Death Penalty, 1985-1989; 1991; 1993; 1996 (Box 1 (5-Subject Files), Folder 2)
- Resource Files, 1983-2000; 6; 1 cubic foot
  This series includes conference materials, journals, magazines, newsletters of various death penalty abolition organizations, personal or organizational research papers, and miscellaneous materials. Miscellaneous files contain campaign materials, booklets, book pamphlets, publications, like an essay by a prisoner on death row, letters written by others on death penalty issues, and lists of executions. Material published in France and Switzerland is also included. The files are arranged alphabetically by categories of materials. Materials within the files are also arranged in alphabetical order by the title of each item.
  - Conference Materials, 6.1 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 1)
    - a. National Conference on Wrongful Convictions and the Death Penalty, 1998 November 13-1998 November 15
    - b. Living Our Faith, April 8-11, 1999
  - Journals, 6.2 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 2)
    - a.Journal of Prisoners on Prison
      v.5 1993, v.6 1995.
    - b.The Texas Observer, April 22, 1988
  - Magazines, 6.3 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 3)
    - a. Concepts, v. 10, No. 1, 3, 5, 1994
    - b.Das Magazin, v. 2, no. 48, 1995
    - c.Hands Off Cain, 1994 January; 1997 October-1997 December; 1998 May-1998 July
  - Magazines, 6.4 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 4)
    - a.The Other Side, 1997 September-1997 December
    - b.The Plough
      no. 42, 1995, no. 50, 1996.
    - c.Passage, Spring 1996
    - d.Prison Life, 1994 June
    - e.SOS Torture, 1994 March-1994 April
    - f.The Witness, v. 80, no. 9, 1997 September
  - Newsletters, 6.5 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 5)
    - a.Case Matters, v. 3, issue 3, 2000 November
    - b.The Executioner, 1994 October-1994 December
    - c.The Feather, Autumn 1995
    - d.FFL News and Notes, Spring 1996; 1998 January
    - e.Justica, 2000 July-2000 October
    - f.Kansas Coalition Against the Death Penalty, 2000 September
    - g.Moratorium News, Summer-Fall 2000
    - h.NCADP National Execution Alert, 2000 December
    - i.News about the Death Penalty, 1996 January-1996 February
    - j.The New Jersey Abolitionist, 1996 April 20
    - k.Pennsylvania Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, Summer 1995
    - l.Florida Prison Legal Perspectives, 2000 May-2000 June
    - m.The Pilgrimage, 1999 September-1999 October; 2000 July-2000 August; 2000 September-2000 October; 2000 November-2000 December
    - n.The Quaker Abolitionist, Spring 1995
    - o.Resist Newsletter, 2000 December
    - p.The Sentry, Summer 2000
    - q.VADP Action, v. 8, no. 2, Fall 2000
    - r.The Vision, 2000 April
    - s.Washington Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, v. 15, no. 4, v. 16, no.1
  - Research Papers, 6.6 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 6)
    - a. Brown, Henry. "Ain't No Justice: Death Sentencing Issues in Oklahoma City", Undated
    - b. Greene, Charla. "American Women Prisoners: Our Invisible Sisters", 1994
  - Research Papers, 6.7 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 7)
    - a. Phil Noble Associates. "Analysis of the Death Penalty and Political Campaigns", 1992 July
    - b. Cambridge Survey Research Inc. "Attitudes in the State of Florida on the Death Penalty", 1986 May
    - c. Grasmick, Harold G. and Bursik, Robert, Jr. "Attitudes of Oklahomans Toward the Death Penalty", 1988 December
    - d. Haney, Craig. "Californians Attitudes About the Death Penalty", 1989
  - Research Papers, 6.8 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 8)
    - a. Aarons, Dwight. "Can Inordinate Delay Between A Death Sentence and Execution Constitute Cruel and Unusual Punishment?"Seton Hall Law Review, v. 29, no. 1, 1998
    - b. Harding, Roberta M. "Capital Punishment as Human Sacrifice", Undated
    - c. Gilbert, Catherine. "Capital Punishment in New South Wales", 1993
  - Research Papers, 6.9 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 9)
    - a. Physicians for Human Rights, "Cruel and Inhumane Treatment: the Use of Four Point Restraint in the Onondaga County Public Safety Building Syracuse", New York, 1993 May
    - b. Mello, Michael, "Death and His Lawyers: Crazy Joe Spaziano and the Death of the Florida Volunteer Lawyers Resource Center", 1995 August
    - c. Mello, Michael, "Death and His Lawyers: Some Thoughts on the Reinstatement of Capital Punishment In New York State", Undated
    - d. Gert, Heather J. "The Death Penalty and Victims Rights: Legal Advance Directives", Undated
    - e. "The Death Penalty: An Issue for Moral Deliberation", 1990
    - f. Rosenberg, Karl H. "Death Row 1998, Texas, Arizona, California, Visits to Inmate
    - g. Cochran, John K. "Deterrence or Brutalization?: An Impact Assessment of Oklahoma's Return to Capital Punishment", 1993 July
  - Research Papers, 6.10 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 10)
    - a. Aarons, Dwight. "Getting Out of This Mess: Steps Toward Addressing and Avoiding Inordinate Delay in Capital Cases"Northwestern University School of Law, v. 89, no. 1, Fall 1998
    - b. "History of the Victims and Crime", Undated
    - c. House of Commons Official Reports. Parliamentary Debates, 1993 July
    - d. Harding, Roberta M. "Human Sacrifice and Capital Punishment: Societal Values as Depicted in Literature", Undated
    - e. Von Sturler, Alice. "An Introduction to the American Criminal Appellate Procedure in Death Penalty Cases", 1994
    - f. Bright, Steohen B. "Is Fairness Irrelevant?: The Evisceration of Federal Habeas Corpus Review and Limits on the Ability of State Courts to Protect Fundamental Rights"Washington and Lee Law Review, v. 54, no. 1, Winter 1997
    - g. Gert, Heather J. "Is it Rational to Support Capital Punishment?", 2000 October
  - Research Papers, 6.11 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 11)
    - a. Streib, Victor L. "The Juvenile Death Penalty Today", 1991 October
    - b. Mello, Michael. "Legal Ethics"Criminal Law Bulletin, Undated
    - c. Mello, Michael. "A Letter on a Lawyer's Life of Death"South Texas Law Review, v. 38, 1997
    - d. Chaney, Ben and Domer, Matthew. "National Commission on Capital Punishment: A De Novo Review of Capital Punishment in the United States of America", Undated
    - e. New York Public Opinion Poll: The Death Penalty Executive Summary, 1989
    - f. "Restorative Justice: A Discussion Paper on Crime and Justice", 1990 March
  - Research Papers, 6.12 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 12)
    - a. Gross, Samuel R. "The Romance of Revenge: Capital Punishment in America", 1992
    - b. Smykla John, "Study of the Impact of Capital Punishment on Death Row Inmate Families", Undated
    - c. Geyer, Anne B. "Study on Media Coverage of the Death Penalty", 1989 September
    - d. Hartman, Joan F. "Unusual Punishment: The Domestic Effects of International Norms Restricting the Application of the Death Penalty"University of Cincinnati Law Review, v. 52, no. 3, 1983
  - Miscellaneous, 6.13 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 13)
    - a. Allridge, James V., III Deadly Executioner, 1995
    - b.Death Penalty Kit, 1991 September
    - c. Doss, Joe Morris.The Death Penalty - Law and Morality, Cases study, 1988
    - d.The Death Penalty: The Religious Community Calls for Abolition, Undated
    - e. Death Row Inmates Active Roster, Florida Department of Corrections, February, 1995
    - f. D.H Heath, Pamphlet, Undated
    - g. Endeavor Project, Memorandum, 1993 February 8
    - h. Execution List Update, Pennsylvania Department of Corrections, 1995 June 23
    - i. Execution Witness List, Texas Department of Criminal Justice, 1993 August
    - j. International Federation of Action by Christians for the Abolition of Torture Action Campaign, "The Death Penalty In the USA", Camping Material, 1995
  - Miscellaneous, 6.14 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 14)
    - a.Instead of Prisons: Handbook for Abolitionists, Handbook, Undated
    - b. The Lamp of Hope, Campaign material, Undated
    - c. Letter by Michael Mello about Joe Spanziano Case, 1995 May 29
    - d. Letter by Michael Mello about Professor William Fischel's Views on Death Penalty, 1995 May 12
    - e. Letter by Tom Miller to members of the Iowa General Assembly with Death Penalty Background Information of Iowa Attorney General's Office, 1997 January
    - f. Letters to Madeleine K. Albright about the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations and Article 36, 1997 May 14
    - g. Lobby Against the Death Penalty, Campaign Material, 1997 May 1
    - h. Van Hoewijk, Japp.Procedure 769, Synopsis for a Documentary on the events Surrounding an Execution, 1993 August
  - Miscellaneous, 6.15 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 15)
    - a.Reflections on Dead Man Walking, Booklet, 2000
    - b.A Saga of Shame: Racial Discrimination and the Death Penalty, Undated
    - c. TASK, Texans Against State Killing, Campaign Material, 1991 April
    - d.Trial for Life: A Manual for Volunteers Preparing Mitigation Evidence for Capital Murder Trials, 1988 July
  - Miscellaneous, MRAP, Campagne Sauver Mumia, Campaign Material, 1995 (Box 1 (6-Resource Files), Folder 16)